（キラービー）九尾チャクラモード。
The Nine Tails' Chakra Mode.
夜道を照らすにゃ便利。
Great for lighting the night road,
命を削るリスクもあれば
いいこともある　表裏。
could cost me my life
like a double-edged knife.
（八尾）ナルトも　九尾チャクラモードを
使えるようになったとはいえ→
Naruto may have learned to
use Nine Tails' Chakra Mode,
but he hasn't made
the Nine Tails his friend.
九尾と
仲よくなったわけじゃねえからな。
ナルトのチャクラは
九尾に取られ続けている…。
Nine Tails continues to
sap Naruto's chakra.
チャクラがゼロになりゃ　ナルトは死ぬ…。
When Naruto's chakra
reaches zero, he'll die.
Oh yeah. But Naruto's tension's high.
Be a shame to stop that passion…
ハーイ！　だが　今のナルトはハイテンション！
止めるにゃ　もったいない
あのパッション！
九尾チャクラを　懐中電灯代わりに
するのはいいが…。
It's okay to use Nine Tails' chakra
like a flashlight.
離されず
ちゃんと　ついていけよ　ビー！
But stick close to him, Bee!
ヤー！
You got it.
（九尾）ナルト…。
Naruto…
（九尾）わしのチャクラを
ぞんざいに扱いよる…。
You're always so careless
with my chakra.
お前の中に　ずっといて→
I've been inside you,
watching you for a long time.
お前を　ずっと見てきたが…。
ナルト…。
Naruto…
お前は　いつも甘い…。
You are still so naïve.
((ナルト：この戦争は→
I will settle this war by myself!
全部　俺一人でケリをつける！
憎しみも痛みも　全部
俺が　まとめて引き受ける！
I will bear all of the hatred
and the pain!
(俺の役目だ！))
That is my duty!
俺のチャクラのおかげで→
Thanks to my chakra, looks like
you've put on some weight.
激ヤセから
少しは　元に戻ったみてえだな。
しかし　珍しいじゃねえかよ　九尾。
But it's not like you, Nine Tails…
to start up a conversation.
お前のほうから
話しかけてくるなんてよ。
いよいよ　寂しくて→
I know you're starting to
get lonely and want to talk,
話し相手がほしくなったのは
わかっけど→
今は忙しいんだ。
あとにしてくれ！
but I'm busy now!
Let's do this later!
戦争を本当に
１人で片づけられると→
Do you seriously think you can
end this war by yourself?
思っているのか？
そりゃ　無理ってもんだ。
It's impossible.
お前も　敵の規模の大きさは
うすうす　感じ取っただろう…。
I'm sure you've sensed
how huge the enemy is.
それに　あのマダラのことだ…。
This is Madara we're talking about.
There's no telling what he'll do.
何を仕掛けてくるか　わからんぞ。
なんなら　わしの力を…。
You're welcome to use my power…
フン…　もう
その手にゃ　のらねえよ！
I'm not falling for that anymore!
フフフフ…
少しは頭が回るようになったか。
You've gotten a bit smarter, I see.
ったく…　みえみえだってえの！
That was so obvious!
話は戦争のあとだ　じゃあな。
We'll talk after the war.
See ya!
（九尾）仲間が殺されれば
それに伴う憎しみが生まれる…。
If your comrades are killed,
hatred will rise.
そうなる前に
相手をすべて倒すつもりか？
Are you planning to defeat
the enemy before that happens?
どのみち　相手を倒せば
敵からの憎しみを受ける…。
If you defeat the enemy,
they'll bear hatred towards you.
それを　すべて
自分で受け止められると→
Do you honestly think you can take
all of that on yourself?
本気で　そう思っているのか？
Stop treating me…
いつまでも…
俺をナメてんじゃねえぞ！
like I'm stupid!
Unison Sign
いつまでも…
俺をナメてんじゃねえぞ！
Unison Sign
Stop treating me
like I'm stupid!
お前は　わかっていない！
甘いのだ！
You don't understand a thing!
You're naïve!
お前は　本当に
皆の憎しみを消し→
Can you honestly take on and
erase everyone's hatred?!
受け止めることができるのか！？
The war has already started.
もう戦争は　始まっている。
戦死者も多く出ているはずだ。
There must be a considerable
amount of casualties already.
♪～
And, the resulting hatred.
その分　憎しみもな。
そもそもだ。
First of all, Sasuke,
who used to be with you,
お前のそばにいたサスケは
ずっと憎しみに囚われていた。
has been gripped by hatred
for a long time.
Have you ever been able
to do anything for him?
だが　そのサスケもお前がどうにか
できたことがあったのか？
あの日だ　そうだ。
Ever since that day…
That's right, you've known it
ever since that day.
あの日からお前は
気づいていたはずだ。
♪～
NINJA ACADEMY
《俺ってば
誰とやりあうんだ？
Who am I going against?
どこのどいつだってばよ。
Who's my guy?
犬帽子か　フードグラサンか？
The kid with the doggy cap?
The hooded kid with the shades?
それとも》
Or…
Um…Sensei…
((チョウジ：あの　先生…。
（イルカ）なんだ？
What is it?
あんまり友達を殴ったりは
したくないんですけど。
I don't want to fight my friend.
いや　そういうんじゃなくてだな。
No, this isn't about hitting.
これは　伝統的な忍組手だ。
This is just some traditional
Shinobi Hand-to-Hand Combat.
かつての火影たちも
この忍組手で鍛錬し→
Even the Hokage
who came before,
trained and got stronger by sparring…
力をつけてだな。
Umm…
（シカマル）あの　先生。
Sensei, you can put me down
for going out of bounds.
俺　場外ってことで
負けでいいっすから→
次のやつに進めてください。
お　おい！
Please move on to
the next ones up.
H-Hey!
訓練だろうが何だろうが
勝敗をつける以上　勝負は勝負。
You might call this training
or whatever,
but if there's going to be a winner,
it's got to be a match.
なら　さっさと
白黒つけちまったほうが→
Since that's the case,
wouldn't it save you trouble
by just deciding
who wins at the start?
めんどくさくなくっていいっしょ。
ハァ…。
He really has no motivation.
He'll never make chunin.
（キバ）やる気ねえな　あいつ。
一生　中忍にはなれねえな。
（シノ）いや　そうとはかぎらない。
No, not necessarily.
Huh?
なぜなら　一生は長い。
Life is long.
A lot could happen.
その間にいろいろ。
Man, you're sure fixated
on the minor details!
なんだお前　細けえよ！
That Shikamaru,
he's the most trouble of all!
（いの）まったく　シカマルのやつ→
あんたが　一番
めんどくさいっての！
チョウジもいくじなしだし！
And you, Choji,
you've got no guts!
（サクラ）いのちゃん
あの子たち知り合いなの？
Ino, do you know those boys?
まあ　親がね。
Yeah well, our parents…
Forget it…
もういい。
シカマル　チョウジ　和解の印を。
Shikamaru, Choji…
give the Unison Sign.
Oh, I forgot.
あ　忘れてた。
I'm sorry, Shikamaru.
ごめんよ　シカマル。
いいよ。
Forget it… You were never good
at stuff like this.
お前　こういうの苦手だしな。
俺もめんどくせえし。
It's a drag for me, too.
うん　和解の印はできたな。
Good, you've done
the Unison Sign.
え～　次。　うずまきナルト。
Next, Naruto Uzumaki!
ヨッシャ！
Yes!
あの子って…。
Is he the one…?
My parents said not to
speak to him.
うちの親が
話しちゃダメだって。
He's one guy I don't want
to be paired with.
私　あいつの
相手だけはしたくない。
And Sasuke Uchiha.
Step forward.
そして　うちはサスケだ。
２人とも出てこい。
Sasuke!
キャー　サスケ君！
サスケ君！
Sasuke!
私が　サスケ君と
和解の印を結びたかった！
I wish I could do
the Unison Sign with Sasuke!
サスケ君　頑張って！
Do your best, Sasuke!
相手なんて　ボッコボコよ！
Pound your opponent!
《なんだ　あいつ
クールぶりやがってよ。
What's with him acting so cool?!
チクショウ…　モテモテのこいつ倒して→
Damn it! I'll take down
Mr. Popular
俺が　モテモテだってばよ！》
and show her who
she should be looking at!
I'm not gonna lose. No way!
ヨッシャ
ぜってえ負けねえってばよ！
（ヒナタ）が…　頑張って　ナルト…。
H-Hang in there…Naru…
サスケく～ん！
Sasuke!
It'll be Naruto Uzumaki
versus Sasuke Uchiha.
では　これより
うずまきナルト　対　うちはサスケの…。
きやがれ！　うすらトンカチ！
Come on, you idiot!
こら　ナルト！　ちゃんと　利き手で
組手前の対立の印をしろ！
Naruto! Make the proper Spar Sign!
それが　礼儀だ。
It's part of the etiquette!
The heck with all that!
んなことは　どうでもいいからさ→
さっさと　こいつ
倒させてくれってばよ！
Hurry up and
let me defeat this guy!
今から　俺ってば
モテモテになるんだから！
I'm going to become popular!
（サスケ）くだらねえ。
望みどおり　ソッコーで…。
What a waste of time…
I'll make it quick,
just like you want.
Hold on, you two!
待て　お前ら！　ったく…。
For crying out loud!
この　忍組手は
昔から守られてきた→
Shinobi Hand-to-Hand Combat
is a traditional training method
passed down through
the generations.
伝統的な訓練方式だ。
形式的すぎる作法もあるが→
It might be stuffy etiquette,
アカデミーでは　基礎から教える。
これも大切なことだ。
but here at the Academy,
we start with the basics.
It matters!
まずは組手前に　必ず片手印を
相手に向ける行為だが→
You always start by showing
your opponent a one-handed sign,
両手印で　術を発動する所作の
半分を意味し→
which represents half of the two hands
used when unleashing a jutsu,
これから戦う意志を示す。
and displays
your intention to fight!
これが　対立の印だ。
This is called the Spar Sign.
組手が終わり　決着のあと→
After the sparring is done
and the victor is decided,
お互い　対立の印を前に出し→
both partners present
the Spar Sign,
重ね合わせ　結び
和解の印として→
then bring their hands together
to form the Unison Sign
仲間であることの意志を示す。
as a show of friendship.
ここまでが
忍組手の作法一式だ。
This is the etiquette of
hand-to-hand combat.
Are you listening, Naruto?!
聞いてんのか？　ナルト！
説明　２回目だぞ！
This is the second time
I've explained it!
はいはい。
「はい」は　１回でいいんだよ！
Yeah, yeah.
One "yes" is sufficient, you fool!
バカモノ！
わかったってばよ。
I get it.
Naru…
Pound him, Sasuke!
ぶっ倒しちゃって～　サスケく～ん！
はじめ！
Start!
イエ～イ！
すげえ　かっけ～！
– Amazing!
– He's so cool!
Sasuke, you're terrific!
サスケ君　すご～い！
すげ…。
Wow…
《こいつ…。
This guy…
この目…。
That look in his eyes…
いつも　俺を見る　みんなの目。
It's the same look that
everyone gives me.
いや　それよりも　もっと強え…。
No, it's stronger than that.
けど…　俺を見てねえ》
But…
But it's not for me.
Sasuke wins!
サスケの勝利！
では　互いに和解の印を。
Now, both of you make
the Unison Sign.
次　いくぞ！
All right, next!
待てよ！
Wait!
俺は　眼中にもねえってか？
クソ野郎！
So you couldn't care less about me,
is that it, you turd?!
No, you piece of crap!
Hard and runny!
いや　むしろ　ウンコだ　ウンコ！
カチカチの　ビチビチヤローが！　バーカ　バーカ！
Stupid! Stupid!
あ～ぁ　頭　悪いな。
The guy's so dumb,
he can't even swear properly.
文句すら　まともに言えてねえよ
あいつ。
I wish he'd make up his mind
便秘なのか　下痢なのか？
どっちか　はっきりしてほしいな。
なぜなら…。
if he's constipated or got the runs.
The reason is…
That's what I mean by you
being fixated on the minor details!
だから　さっきから　細けえよ。
フン…。
何か言えってんだ！
You got something to say to me,
you hard and runny crap-turd?!
この　ガチガチウンコ　ビチビチヤロー！！
忍組手は
神聖な伝統だと言っている！
Ouch!
Didn't I tell you that
Shinobi Hand-to-Hand Combat
is a sacred tradition?!
さっさと和解の印をしろ！
Now hurry up and
make the Unison Sign!
You too, Sasuke!
サスケ　お前もだ！
ったく…。
Damn it…
フン！
やんのか？　落ちこぼれが。
You want a piece of me, you loser?!
Hey! That's enough! Both of you!
こら　いいかげんにしろ　お前ら！
Naruto's the worst!
最低！　ナルト！
何だ？　あいつ。
What is up with him?
ベェ～！！
思い出したようだな。
Looks like you remembered.
そしてだ…
あれから　サスケは　どうなった？
And then, what happened to Sasuke?
お前は
憎しみを消してやれたのか？
Were you able to erase his hatred?
いや　違う。　その逆だ。
No, in fact, just the opposite…
((いいかげんに
目が覚めたかよ！
Have you snapped out of it yet?
親も兄弟もいねえ　てめえに
俺の何が　わかるってんだよ！
You have no siblings
or parents.
How could you understand
anything about me?!
はじめから
独りっきりだった　てめえに→
You've been on your own
since the beginning!
(俺の何が　わかるってんだ！))
What makes you think
you know anything about me?
♪～
((ナルト…
お前が　今さら何を言おうと→
Naruto…
You can't change me,
no matter what you say to me now.
俺は変わらねえ。
俺は　お前も里のやつらも
１人残らず　全員を殺す！
I'm going to kill each and
every person in the Leaf,
including you!
なぁ　ほんとに
そんな道しか　ねえのか？
Sasuke, is that really
the only way?
そうだ。
Yes.
行きつくところ　お前の選択は→
So your only choices are
to kill me and become
the hero who saved the village,
俺を殺して
里を守った英雄になるか→
(俺に殺されて
ただの負け犬に　なるかだ！))
or to be killed by me,
and be known as just a loser!
ますます
やつの憎しみは大きくなった。
His hatred has grown
even stronger!
最も　身近にいた仲間ですら
そうなのだ。
It happened to
your closest friend!
つまり　お前は誰であろうと→
In other words…
regardless of who
you're dealing with,
憎しみを消してやることも
受け止めることも　できやしない！
you can neither erase their hatred
nor take it on yourself!
で…。
So?
話は　終わりか？
Are you finished?
なんだと！？
What?!
だからって　俺が怖気づいて
何もしねえとでも？
Are you trying to scare me
into doing nothing?
そうなりゃ
お前の思うツボだもんな　九尾。
That's exactly what you want,
isn't it, Nine Tails?
おい。
んっ！？
Hey…
お前こそ　甘いんだよ。
You're the one who's naïve!
お前は　サスケ１人　救えないのに→
Who are you to be so confident…
when you couldn't
even save Sasuke?
なんで　そんな強気でいられる！？
自分が決めたことに
疑問　持ったら終わりだ。
Once you question
your own beliefs, it's over.
サスケは　なんとかしてみせるし
戦争だって　どうにかしてみせる。
I will help Sasuke somehow,
and I will do something about this war!
《わしを　また封印する気か！？
Does he intend to seal me again?
しかも　あんなガキに！》
On top of which,
inside a kid like that?!
((こら　アホギツネ！
Hey, you stupid fox!
俺の体に　泊めてやってんだから→
I've been letting you
stay inside my body,
家賃として
お前のチャクラを貸しやがれ！
so why don't you pay me
some rent,
and lend me some of
your chakra?
仙法。
Sage Mode…
超大玉！
Rasengan…Super Barrage!
螺旋多連丸！
♪～
もう　ひと押し～！
Just one more round!
What is this power?!
《なんだ　この力は！？》
♪～
これは…。
This is…the Nine Tails'…
これが九尾の…。
ナルト…。　わしを…。
Naruto…
You've…
You've made me angry, Naruto!
わしを怒らせたな！
ナルト！
まだ…　こんだけの力が。
You still had this much power?
You really are awesome!
やっぱ　すげぇや…　おめえは。
♪～
こりゃあ　六道の…。
Is this the Six Paths'…?!
♪～
You'll regret this, Naruto.
(覚えていろ…ナルト…))
フンッ。
あのチンチクリンが随分と
盾突くようになったじゃねえか。
The little child thinks
he's grown up, does he?
なぁ　九尾…。　俺はな…。
Ya know, Nine Tails, I…
I'm going to come after
いつか　おめえの中の憎しみも→
all that hate inside you
as well, some day!
どうにかしてやりてぇと思ってる。
俺を　さんざん苦しめた
お前だけど…。
You've put me through
a lot of pain,
憎しみに振り回されんのは→
but I know that
it doesn't feel good
to be at the mercy of your hatred…
いい気がしねえってのは
俺も知ってっから。
キッ！　お前はバカか！
Are you stupid?!
わしは九尾だぞ！
I'm the Nine Tails, you know!
チンチクリンにどうこうされるほど→
Some little child can't change me!
落ちぶれちゃいねえし→
I am hatred!
わしは憎しみのかたまりだ。
Then it's okay!
なら　オーケーだ！
I'm no longer a little child,
俺はチンチクリンじゃねえし
そっちのほうがやりがいがある！
and it's more challenging that way!
じゃあな！
Later!
♪～
Nine Tails…
《九尾。　確かに俺は
大甘かもしんねえ。
You might be right about me
being extremely naïve.
でも　俺の中に　父ちゃんも
母ちゃんもいてくれたように→
But in my heart,
you've always been with me,
お前は
ずっと俺と一緒にいてくれた。
like a mother and father
stays with their child.
俺の気持も成長も
全部お前は知ってるんだもんな。
You know everything
about how I feel
and how I've grown up.
You might no
ほんとは
嫌だったのかもしんねえけど→
おめえは俺のことを
見つめ続けていてくれたんだ。
だからよ…　もうちょっと
そこで俺のこと見ていてくれ》
《サスケ…　おめえのこともそうだ。
おめえは俺なんて　はなっから
眼中になかったんだろうけど→
俺は…　お前のこと
ずっと見てたんだぜ》
そうさ　サスケも戦争も
俺がなんとかする！
ヨウ！　ピッカピカライトなナルト！
満月のナイトに深刻な表情。
もっとライトにいこうぜぇ！　ヤー！
ああん？　おめえ
また九尾とケンカでもしたか？
尾獣モードは九尾とチャクラの綱引き。
チャクラが無くなりゃ命は幕引き。
無茶はやめとけってばよ！
無茶なのは　わかってる。
だけどよ…
自分の言葉は曲げねえ！
それが俺の忍道だってばよ！
飛ばすぜ！
待てってばよ！
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
美空ひばりです。
では　最後まで
ごゆっくりお楽しみください。
『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！　にっぽんの歌』。